Father.
父上
Haven't I told you before?
言うたはずだ
Whether in public or in private,
人前であろうとなかろうと
you should just call me "Master."
私のことは先生と呼べと
"Our bodies are gifts from our parents."
身体髪膚 これを父母に受く
This life of mine is
この茂の血肉は
entirely a gift from you, Father.
全て父上から授かったものです
Had you not taken me in
もし父上がかつて
as your student in Jiankang
剣慷で私を弟子として受け入れ
and guided me so diligently,
熱心にご指導くださらなければ
I would never have reached where I am today.
今の茂はおりません
Everything I believe in and aspire to
この志も
has also been nurtured by your teaching.
父上のお育てなくしてはありえません
I would never dare show you anything but respect.
敬意を欠くわけにはまいりません
Good.
うむ
My good son.
よい息子だ
You are every bit a son of the Xie family.
さすがは謝家の息子だ
You've done well these past few years.
ここ数年 よくやった
You used the reform as a pretext to reshape the salt and iron monopoly
改革を機に塩鉄を動かし
and clear the waterways.
川筋を整備した
The people will remember you
民はお前を記憶し
and support you.
支持するだろう
But the reform
だが この改革は
was ultimately initiated by Xiao Wuyi.
しょせん蕭無衣によって始まったもの
If you want to become
もし お前が
the true ruler of the realm,
この天下の真の主になりたいのなら
you must sweep aside
目の前に立ちはだかる者を
anyone who stands in your way,
この埃のようにな
one by one, like dust.
一つずつ掃き清めねばならん
Xiao Wuyi,
無衣
you need to learn to take what you want.
もっと求めなきゃ
Do you hear me?
聞こえてるの
I hear you.
聞こえてる
Good.
ならいいわ
You're really drunk.
もう 本当に酔ってる
I'm not.
酔ってないわ
I still have a New Year's gift for you.
まだ新年の贈り物を渡してないし
What do you think?
どう
My red steed.
赤駒
My Miraculous Craft has made a lot of money,
“妙手”は稼げるのよ
♪ You see my move under rebellious cover ♪
だから買い戻してきた
You're going to the battlefield,
戦場に行くなら
so you need the finest horse.
最高の馬に乗らないと
It can bring you home.
この子があなたを家に連れ帰ってくれる
Yaoyao.
夭夭
I'll do my best...
頑張って
to spend every New Year with you.
毎年一緒に新年を過ごそう
Wait, not this one.
待て これではない
I have a Hetian white jade crown
余にはホータン白玉の玉冠がある
that Yaoyao gave me.
夭夭が贈ってくれたものだ
Today
今日は
is the day she'll be officially invested.
彼女が冊封される晴れの日だ
I want to wear that one.
それを着けて式に臨みたい
Yes.
はっ
To Prince Jing'an's Mansion.
靖安王府へ
Grand Tutor Xie,
太傅
have you heard?
お聞きになりましたか
Something terrible happened at the grain canal.
兵糧の道で一大事が
The Xiao family embezzled funds for the canal.
蕭家が水路補修費を横領し
They replaced river sand with mud and silt,
川砂の代わりに泥砂を使い
causing the grain canal to collapse,
食糧輸送路が崩壊
and nearly 100 laborers were killed or injured.
労役で100名近くが死傷したとのことです
The County Sheriff has hanged himself.
県尉はすでに首を吊って自害
The outraged crowds have already reached Jiankang.
今や怒れる民が剣慷に集まっています
There are so many guests today.
今日は大勢来ていますね
Yes.
ええ
Congratulations, congratulations.
おめでとうございます
Please come in.
どうぞ
Why have so many
なぜ今日は
officials' families come to attend the ceremony today?
これほど多くの役人のご家族が観礼に
Congratulations, congratulations.
おめでとうございます
Did you invite them?
お前が呼んだのか
Of course not.
俺なわけない
It must've been Wuyi.
無衣に決まってる
I didn't.
俺でもない
Then...
じゃあ誰だ
Father, don't worry about it.
父上 ご心配なく
It's not every day Wuyi throws such a grand affair.
無衣が珍しく派手にやるんで
Of course they came to help him make a good showing.
皆で盛り上げてやらないと
His Highness Prince Qi has arrived!
岐王殿下のお成りです
-Your Highness.
殿下
Congratulations.
おめでとうございます
I'm not late, am I?
吉刻には間に合いましたかな
Your Highness has arrived at just the right time.
殿下 ちょうどよいお着きで
Thank you.
礼を言う
From now on,
これより
we are no longer brothers,
そなたと私の間に兄弟の縁はない
but ruler and subject.
あるのは君臣のみ
Who is beating the drum?
太鼓を打ち鳴らすのは何者だ
This must be a grave injustice.
よほどの訴えがあるようですな
Someone is sounding the Petition Drum.
誰かが登聞鼓を
Petition Drum?
登聞鼓
It's struck only when the people
民に大冤あり
have suffered a great injustice
あるいは敵軍来襲の際に
or when enemy forces are invading.
登聞鼓は打ち鳴らされる
Anyone who dares to strike that drum,
この鼓を打ち鳴らした者は
whether their accusation is true or false,
訴えの真偽を問わず
must first endure 30 strikes of the cane
まず杖刑三十を受け
to prove they're not making a false accusation.
誣告でないと証明せねばならぬ
Wouldn't that leave them dead or crippled?
では死ぬか大けがですな
Therefore, unless someone has genuinely suffered a serious injustice,
ゆえに真の冤罪でなければ
no one would risk their own life like this.
自ら死地に赴く者はおらぬ
Something major is about to happen at court.
近頃 朝廷で何かあったに違いない
It has begun.
始まった
My Lord!
殿
Who is it you intend to accuse?
おぬしらは誰を訴える
We accuse the Commander of the Beifu Army,
我らが訴えるは北府の統帥
the Heir of Prince Jing'an, Xiao Wuyi,
靖安王世子 蕭無衣
and his brother, Xiao Yao, supervisor of the grain canal works.
並びに靖安王府 兵糧道監修 蕭堯です
What?
何だと
My Lord, please seek justice for us!
殿 我らの無念をお晴らしください
The auspicious hour has arrived.
吉刻となりました
We respectfully invite Prince Qi, the Regent, to bestow
監国 岐王殿下には
the imperial decree and seal upon the Consort of the Heir of Prince Jing'an
靖安王世子妃に冊宝を授けていただき
and read out the proclamation of investiture.
冊封の勅旨を宣読いただきます
Report!
申し上げます
Where are the accused, Xiao Wuyi and Xiao Yao?
罪人 蕭無衣と蕭堯はどこだ
I pay my respects to Your Highness.
臣 殿下に拝謁いたします
Your Highness,
私が参りましたのは
I have no wish to disrupt
世子妃様の冊封の儀を
the Heir's Consort investiture ceremony.
妨害する意図ではございません
But the Petition Drum has been struck.
登聞鼓が鳴ったため
According to the laws of Ye,
大鄴の律法により
the main culprits must be detained immediately:
首犯である蕭世子と
Young Lord Xiao and Eldest Young Master Xiao.
蕭家の若様を即刻 拘束いたします
Please forgive the offense.
お二人とも ご無礼
How insolent!
無礼者
Today, at the investiture ceremony,
本日は冊封の儀だ
I'd like to see who dares arrest them!
誰が捕らえられるものか
The Ministry of Justice never
我ら廷尉府が人を捕らえるに
makes arrests without evidence.
証拠もなく行うことはない
The grain canal in Hexi has collapsed,
河西の兵糧の道が崩落
causing over 1,000 casualties and public outrage.
死傷者は千を超え 民の怒りは頂点に達しております
Our investigation found
調べでは
that County Magistrate Wei Min, a man of humble birth,
県令の魏閩は世子が
was personally promoted by Young Lord Xiao.
自ら抜擢した寒門の出
In his home,
奴の家から
we found years of correspondence between him
世子と若様との
and Young Lord Xiao and Eldest Young Master Xiao,
長年にわたる書簡と
along with 1,000 taels of gold.
黄金千両が見つかりました
Moreover, the letters reveal evidence
さらに書簡からは
that the Xiaos embezzled the canal repair funds
蕭氏が水路補修費を横領し
and abused their power for personal gain.
権力を私物化した証拠が
Commandant of Justice, if the sons are guilty,
廷尉 息子に罪があるなら
shouldn't the father be guilty as well?
父親の私にも罪があるはずだ
You may arrest the two of them,
二人を捕らえるのはよかろう
but you'll be taking me too!
だが この私も連れて行け
I'd like to see which of you dares!
誰が手出しできるものか
Take Prince Jing'an,
靖安王
the Heir, and Eldest Young Master Xiao
靖安王世子と若様
to the Court of Judicial Review together.
全員を大理寺へ連行せよ
Yes, Your Highness.
御意
Order the Three Judicial Offices to send officials
三司に者を遣わし
to conduct a thorough investigation at the grain canal.
糧道にてこの件を徹底的に調査させよ
If they have been wronged,
もし冤罪ならば
I will ensure justice is done.
余がその者らのために裁きを下す
If they are guilty...
冤罪でなくば
I will never allow anyone
誰であろうと この余は許さぬ
to escape the law.
法を免れることは
Prince Jing'an, please forgive the offense.
靖安王 失礼いたします
Young Lord Xiao, please.
世子様 こちらへ
Don't worry. I'll be back.
心配するな 必ず戻る
Your Highness, please bestow the decree and seal.
殿下 冊宝をお授けください
Your Highness, please proceed with the investiture.
殿下 礼をお加えください
Young Lord Xiao, you seem so composed.
蕭世子 その落ち着き払ったご様子
Are you that certain
下官には確証が
I won't find conclusive evidence against you?
つかめぬと踏んでおいでですかな
There is a list in my residence
王府には帳簿がある
recording every official
かつて この世子に
who has ever attempted
賄賂を渡そうとした
to bribe me.
役人たちの名簿だ
I've already sent a copy to the Eastern Palace.
名簿はすでに書き写し 東宮へ送った
Now I'll hand the original copy of the list to you.
今 名簿の控えを廷尉殿にお渡しする
If such a list really exists,
そのような帳簿が実在するなら
why didn't you mention it earlier?
なぜ先ほどおっしゃらなかったのですか
Today, before the public,
今日この大勢の前では
the Petition Drum has been struck,
登聞鼓が鳴らされた以上
so you've come bearing the will of the people.
廷尉殿も民の声を背負っておられる
Whether the accusations are true or false,
真偽はどうあれ
they must go through the Court of Judicial Review's process to convince everyone.
大理寺の裁きを受けねば民は納得せぬ
If I hadn't come, it would've damaged your reputation.
私が来なければ 廷尉の名が傷つく
And by coming,
そして私が来たのは
I placed my bet on your competence.
廷尉の能力に懸けたのです
In that case,
そうなると
I should be thanking you, Young Lord Xiao?
私が世子様に感謝せねばなりませんな
There is one more thing
もう一つ
I'd ask you to consider, Commandant of Justice.
廷尉殿に考慮いただきたい儀がある
Please go on, Young Lord Xiao.
世子様 お話しください
I've long heard that you're strict and impartial.
廷尉殿は苛烈にして公平と聞く
However, my father is elderly,
だが 我が父は高齢
and my elder brother's leg is badly crippled.
兄は足の病が重く
Neither could endure torture.
拷問には耐えられぬ
Moreover, every order regarding the grain canal work
それに 糧道の監修に関する政令は
was issued by me.
すべて私が下したものです
If torture is to be used,
いかなる拷問も
I'm willing to endure it in their place.
父と兄に代わり 私が受けましょう
Xiao Wuyi, don't shield me!
蕭無衣 私をかばうな
Since I dared to come in,
中へ入った以上
I am not afraid of interrogation!
尋問など恐れはせぬ
What do you mean by "elderly"?
高齢だと
I'm sturdier than the two of them put together!
儂はあの２人より達者だぞ
Interrogate me if you must!
聞くなら儂に聞け
Rest assured, everyone.
皆様 ご安心を
If this turns out to be a frame-up,
もしこれが冤罪だと分かれば
I will absolutely restore the good name of
下官が必ずや靖安王府の
your household.
潔白を証明いたします
I entered prison
私が入獄したのは
precisely to see
見届けるためだ
just how far
黒幕が
the person behind all this is willing to go.
どこまでやるのかを
Yuanji.
姉上
Mother had some calming tonic
母上は安神湯を召し上がり
and is asleep now.
すでにお休みです
The letters and ledgers in the household
屋敷内の書状や帳簿は
have all been seized.
すべて差し押さえられました
Could it be that the Ministry of Justice
廷尉府が
has been acting under someone's orders,
誰かの差し金で
trying to frame us?
我らを陥れようと
I don't think so.
そうとは思えぬ
Commandant of Justice Lu, who came today,
今日来た陸廷尉は
was newly promoted last year.
昨年 新たに抜擢された者
During these years of reform,
改制以来 この数年
while serving in the provinces,
彼は地方で
he punished commoners who cheated in the marketplace
貧民の不正を摘発し
and sentenced noble clans who seized land by force alike.
名家による土地の囲い込みも裁いてきた
He's a ruthless but upright official
公平無私で
who enforces the law without favor.
一視同仁の酷吏だ
Since he personally came to make the arrest today,
今日 自ら捕らえに来たからには
he surely wouldn't act without evidence.
確かな証拠があるはずだ
The plaintiffs
訴えは
accuse the Beifu Army of embezzling
北府の治水工事で
and taking bribes during the canal repairs,
横領と収賄
and cutting corners on the work—
手抜き工事があり
which caused the grain canal to collapse
兵糧の道が崩落
and killed many conscripted laborers.
労役の者が圧死したと
Yao would never do that.
兄貴がそんなはずない
Letters, ledgers...
書簡と帳簿
Nanxing.
南星
My Lady.
お嬢様
You have a photographic memory for the accounts.
帳簿のことならお見通しでしょう
You've been helping me with the accounts these past years.
ここ数年の帳簿はあなたに手伝ってもらったわ
So help me reconstruct them.
帳簿を復元してちょうだい
Yes.
はい
Ledgers...
帳簿
Letters...
書簡
Handwriting...
筆跡
What's wrong, Yuanji?
どうなさいました 姉上
Nothing.
なんでもないわ
I just suddenly realized
ただ ふと思い出したの
I haven't seen Qing Long and Yan Yue around.
青龍と偃月はどこへ行ったのかしら
Right, where are they?
そういえば 青龍さんと偃月さんは？
Xiao Wuyi and Xiao Ju have been imprisoned.
蕭無衣と蕭駒は投獄した
Have you prepared
偽造を命じた書簡は
the forged correspondence I asked for?
できたか
Afraid it'll be exposed?
発覚が怖いか
For the Xiao family,
蕭家から見れば
this will be a capital offense.
死罪に当たります
They deserve it.
蕭氏の自業自得だ
I won't go back on my promise to you.
約束は違えぬ
I've already requested Prince Qi's approval
岐王殿下に願い出て
to reopen the Lantai gathering.
蘭台会を再開させる
Get up first.
まずは立て
Come on.
さあ
Zhaolin,
昭林
when the time comes...
さすれば
you'll be a student of mine,
そなたは この謝懐帰の弟子だ
and no one will ever
そして二度と
look down on your background again.
出自をさげすむ者はいなくなる
Thank you,
弟子…
Grand Tutor Xie.
謝太傅様
Are those people
裏で
helping you cook the books
偽の帳簿を作らせた者たちは
actually trustworthy?
信用できるのか
They don't know
彼らは何も知らず
what they're doing,
何をしているかも
nor do they know who they're working for.
誰のためかも知りません
Excellent.
よかった
Are you alright?
大丈夫か
Let's go!
早く行け
Hurry.
急げ
Mr. Liu,
柳先生
since when did you become Grand Tutor Xie's lackey?
いつから太傅様の犬になったのです
You knew I collected rare books.
先生は私が蔵書家だとご存じで
Xiao Yao, Xiao Wuyi,
蕭堯様や蕭無衣様
and even Prince Jing'an had all borrowed and annotated them.
蕭老王爺までもが本を借り注釈を付けておられました
So you used me to obtain
先生は私を介し
the handwriting of every member
本の貸し借りを通じて
of the Xiao family by borrowing books from me.
蕭家の皆の筆跡を手に入れた
Back then, when you gave me a deed of debt...
まさか先生が あの時 割り符を返し
I offer this deed of debt
これは割り符だ
as proof
これを証しに
that I'll surely repay the debt someday.
いずれ必ず返す
When you said you'd repay me for saving your life,
命の恩を返すと言った時から
you'd already thought of how you could use me?
私の使い道を考えていたのですか
Absolutely not! I...
違います 私は
I admire you.
お嬢様をお慕いしておりましたが
But I didn't dare to tell you.
告げられずにいました
I knew all along.
とっくに気づいていました
I've frequented the bookstore these past couple of years.
この二年 私が書局に通ったのは
Could you really not tell how I felt about you?
私の気持ちに気づいてほしかったから
It's precisely because I know
分かっていたからこそ
that I'm even more aware I'm not worthy of you.
私がお嬢様にふさわしくないのだと
Whether you were the Consort of the Heir of Prince Jing'an back then
かつての世子妃様にも
or are the head of the He family now,
今の何家の当主様にも
I was never worthy of you.
私は釣り合いません
I'm merely a commoner,
私はただの庶民
full of ideals.
気骨だけが取り柄で
Anyone can trample on me.
誰からもないがしろにされる身です
Only Grand Tutor Xie.
ただ太傅様だけが
He promised me.
約束してくださった
As long as Xiao Wuyi falls
蕭無衣が失脚し
and the noble clans revive the Lantai gathering,
名家が蘭台会を再開すれば
he'll give me an official post.
私に官職を与えるとな
You're the third child in your family.
あなたは三男で
You once studied at Luming Academy
かつて鹿鳴書院で学んでいた
and were classmates with my second brother.
私の次兄とは同窓だったわ
Back then,
当時の私は
I often secretly put on my second brother's clothes
よく次兄の服をこっそり着て
and sneaked into the academy to sit in on lectures.
書院へ聴講しに行ったものよ
We got to know each other over time.
そうするうちに あなたと知り合った
We shared the same interests
私たちは意気投合して
and often studied together.
いつも一緒に学問に励んだわね
It was only then that my brother told you
それで次兄があなたに明かしたの
I was actually a girl.
私が女だと
You were shocked yet delighted
あなたは驚き喜んで
and said you'd return home and ask your parents to arrange our marriage.
故郷に帰り両親に報告すると言った
But just at that time,
でも あいにくその時
my aunt, Empress Dowager He,
叔母である何太后が
was choosing someone from the clan
一族から一人を選び
to marry into Prince Jing'an's household.
靖安王府と縁組させようとなさった
But I was in love with you.
でも私はあなたを想っていたから
After my aunt found out,
それを知った叔母上が
she sent people to kill you.
人を使ってあなたを殺そうとしたの
I thought
私は
you were dead.
もう死んだのだと
But I never imagined
でも思いもしなかった
that day at the bookstore...
あの日 書局で
Pei Runheng?
裴潤恒
I'd see you again.
まさかあなたに再会するなんて
Impossible.
あり得ない
You definitely got the wrong person.
人違いだ
You were born in the Year of the Tiger.
あなたの干支は寅
There's a plum blossom-shaped scar on your left arm.
左腕には梅の花形の傷痕があるわ
You got it when you were protecting me from wild bees while we were
あれは書院の裏山で桑摘みをしていた時
picking mulberries in the back mountain of the academy.
私をかばって野蜂に刺された痕よ
And your handwriting.
それにあなたの筆跡
I would never mistake it.
見間違えるはずがないわ
Then why didn't you tell me sooner?
なら なぜもっと早く言わなかった
In the second year after I married into Prince Jing'an's household,
私が靖安王府に嫁いだ翌年
Empress Dowager He found a pretext
太后が口実を設けて
and convicted your family.
裴家を罪に陥れたの
Your father and brothers died,
あなたの父上と兄上は亡くなり
and your mother, in her despair, took her own life along with your sister.
母上は心労の末 娘を道連れに自害した
I'm a daughter of the He family.
私は何氏の娘
Our families have long been bound by a blood feud.
裴氏とはとうに血の海の恨みがあった
I didn't dare let you remember the past.
あなたに過去を思い出させるのが怖かった
I foolishly convinced myself
自分をだましていたの
that as long as I didn't speak of it,
私が言わなければ
we could have a fresh start together.
あなたとやり直せるはずだと
But I never expected...
でも
I never expected
思いもしなかった
you to be deceived and used by Xie Huaigui.
あなたが謝懐帰にだまされ利用されるなんて
Runheng, you can still turn back now.
三郎 今ならまだ間に合うわ
My right hand is ruined.
右手はもう動かん
I can no longer prove
もはや証明はできん
that those letters and ledgers were forged by me.
あの書簡と帳簿が俺の偽造だとは
You are living proof.
あなたが生きていること自体が証拠よ
Jiayu.
嘉魚さん
What exactly is the crime Grand Tutor Xie intends to pin on the Xiao family?
太傅様は蕭氏を何の罪に問うおつもりです
Treason...
内通
and collaboration with the enemy.
そして謀反
Tell us everything you know.
知っていることをすべて話しなさい
At this point,
もうこうなった以上
Runheng,
三郎
for the sake of the person you once were,
昔の自分のために
don't keep going down this road.
これ以上 過ちを犯さないで
Third Alley, Shanghe Ward.
上河坊三巷だ
The scholars who forged the letters and ledgers
書簡と帳簿を偽造した書生たちは
are all hidden there.
そこに隠されている
If you move quickly,
急げば
you might still be able to save some of them.
生き残りを救えるかもしれん
Too late again.
また一歩遅かったか
The outcome is not yet decided.
まだ勝敗は決しておりませんのに
Prince Qi, don't you think you've come a little early?
岐王のお越しは少し早すぎたのでは
These past few days,
この数日
the evidence has been piling up—
蕭堯は兵糧を横領し
Xiao Yao's corruption in the grain canal project,
蕭駒は軍需物資を売買
and Xiao Ju's sale of military supplies and leaking of military intelligence.
軍事機密を売り渡した罪証も次々と挙がっている
Not just your family—
蕭家だけではない
many of the common-born officials you promoted
そなたが抜擢した寒門の役人も
have been dragged down with you as well.
大勢が芋づる式に発覚した
Now, the public in and out of Jiankang is outraged,
今や剣慷の内外では民衆の怒りが頂点に達している
demanding severe punishment for your family
靖安王府を厳罰に処し
and a strict investigation of common-born officials.
寒門の役人を調査しろと要求している
Do you think you still have a way out,
まだ自分に活路が残されているとでも思うか
Crown Prince Wenxi?
文熹太子
From the day His Majesty returned the Phoenix Heart Token to you,
陛下が雀骨令をそなたにお返しになった日から
I was certain of your identity.
そなたの正体には気づいていた
From supervising the grain canal
兵糧の道の監修から
to charges of treason, it's exactly
敵と通じ国を売るまで
the same pattern as the downfall of the An and Lu families back then.
かつて安陸の二氏が滅ぼされた手口とそっくりだ
Grand Tutor Xie has certainly put a great deal of thought
謝太傅が蕭家に被せた罪名
into choosing the Xiao family's crimes.
誠にご苦心なされたことだ
So you really do know the truth behind the An-Lu case.
やはり安陸の事件の真相を知っていたか
And since you know,
知っているのなら
you should also realize
分かるはずだ
that Grand Tutor Xie isn't leaving you any way out.
太傅が本気で潰しにかかっていると
Xie Jiayu acted fast
謝嘉魚の動きは速い
and found the one who forged the letters and ledgers.
書簡と帳簿を偽造した者を見つけた
But that man's hand is ruined.
だがそいつは手を折られて
He can't testify.
証言はできない
For the sake of our past brotherhood,
かつての兄弟のよしみで
I can spare your whole family...
蕭家一門の命は助けてやろう
I won't agree to the conditions you're about to propose.
そなたの条件は到底飲めない
Hand over the Beifu Army and the Phoenix Heart Token,
北府と雀骨令を差し出せ
and write a divorce agreement.
離縁状を書くのだ
I want you to tell Xie Jiayu yourself
謝嘉魚には自分の口で
that you want to divorce her.
離縁すると伝えろ
Do you honestly think that's possible?
可能だと思うか
I think it is.
可能だと思う
Xie Jiayu is her own person.
謝嘉魚は一個の人間だ
Her life
彼女の人生も
and her feelings
彼女の感情も
should be hers to choose.
すべて彼女自身が選ぶべきだ
You're forcing her to come back to you—
彼女に戻るよう強要するのは
is it because you love her
彼女を愛しているからか
or because you hate me?
それとも私への憎しみからか
That was Xie Jiayu's own wrong choice to begin with.
謝嘉魚が最初から選び間違えたのだ
I'm merely giving her
私は彼女に
a chance to choose again.
選び直す機会を与えているにすぎん
Li Yizhi.
李易之
You shouldn't have dragged the Xiao family
蕭家や
and all those common-born officials into this.
他の寒門を巻き込むべきではなかった
Do you really think all those commoners you promoted
そなたが抜擢した寒門たちが
are people of both talent and good character?
皆 才覚も人品も優れているとでも
Cruel and corrupt officials mostly come from humble origins.
酷吏や汚吏の多くは寒門の出だ
The common people have long since grown to despise the reforms.
民はとうに改革を心底憎んでいる
Even if everything you've done was meant to save the realm,
そなたの行いが大鄴を救うためだとしても
then tell me—
では聞くが
how many people can truly understand your intentions?
そなたの行いを真に理解できる者が何人いる
And how many would actually appreciate them?
そなたに恩を感じる者が何人いるというのだ
All you'll get is more and more people
そなたの死を望む者が
wanting you dead.
増えるだけだ
And you don't fully know
そしてそなたは
this father of yours either.
自分の父親をよく分かっていない
Xiao Ju was not dragged into this.
蕭駒は巻き込まれたのではない
He and your birth mother
彼とそなたの母后は
were both perpetrators of the An-Lu wrongful case.
安陸の冤罪事件の犯人だ
He's selfish and cowardly
彼は利己的で卑劣だ
and will abandon all moral principles for his own interests.
私利私欲のためなら是非も問わず手段も選ばない
The downfall of the Xiao family
蕭氏の滅亡は
is inevitable.
必然だったのだ
If you really want to protect Xie Jiayu,
本気で謝嘉魚を守りたいのなら
divorce is the only path left.
離縁が唯一の道だ
The grain canal collapsed, the Xiao family embezzled,
兵糧の道の崩壊 蕭氏の汚職
Xiao Wuyi was imprisoned, and the ruler and his subject became estranged.
蕭世子の投獄 君臣の不和
You're very smart.
賢いな
You know that the truth of the An-Lu case
安陸の二氏の事件の真相こそ
is Xie Huaigui's real obsession
謝懐帰の心残りだと知っていたか
and that if he learns
もし彼が
Xiao Ju knew of the injustice back then
蕭駒が当時 冤罪と知りつつ
yet concealed it,
隠蔽したと知れば
he will never let the Xiao family go.
決して蕭家を許しはしないだろう
Xiao Wuyi has been imprisoned.
蕭無衣が投獄された
Are you happy?
お喜びですの
If he dies,
彼奴が死ねば
Xie Jiayu will be left without anyone to rely on.
謝嘉魚は後ろ盾を失い
Your brother is now the Regent in name and in fact.
そなたの兄上は名実ともに監国となる
You can also return to Southern Ye.
そなたも南鄴へ帰れる
I belong
この身は今や
to you now, Your Highness.
王爺様のものです
And I'll never go back in this life.
生涯 南鄴へ戻ることはありませぬ
Without Xiao Wuyi, the Beifu Army
北府軍は蕭無衣を失えば
has lost its fighting spirit.
戦力を失い
It'll never again be a match for Your Highness's Black Eagle Army.
もはや王爺様の黒鷹軍の敵ではありませぬ
From now on, the border will be secure.
これで辺境の憂いもなくなります
I should congratulate Your Highness.
わらわが王爺様にお祝いを申し上げるべきですわ
Is that so?
そうか
You're helping your brother eliminate his greatest rival,
兄上のために政敵を始末しただけだろうに
and yet you still find such a pretty way to put it.
よくもまあ これほど美辞麗句を並べられるものだ
Your Highness,
王爺様
all the warriors participating in today's mounted archery contest
本日の走馬穿楊に参加する勇士たちが
have arrived.
皆 到着いたしました
The cattle, sheep, and Ye slaves have also been brought into the arena.
牛や羊 そして鄴奴も馬場に入っております
I know.
分かった
Then let me help Your Highness change.
では王爺様のお着替えを
Lejun.
楽君
What's wrong?
どうしたのですか
My child...
我が子が
Our child?
私たちの子よ
You did this on purpose.
わざとでしょう
You didn't want him.
この子が要らないのね
You didn't want our child, did you?
私たちの子が要らないのでしょう
I...
私は
didn't...
違います
Lejun. Lejun!
楽君 楽君
We were still a step too late.
やはり一歩遅かったか
We only have Liu Zhaolin as a witness,
証人は柳昭林しかおらぬ
but his hand is ruined.
だが奴の手は潰されてしまった
I'm afraid his testimony alone won't convince anyone.
これでは皆を納得させられん
Not too late.
遅くはない
At least now we know who's behind it.
少なくとも黒幕は分かった
Jiayu.
嘉魚
There is something
話さねばならぬことが
you need to know now.
ある
If Xiao Wuyi keeps pushing himself like this,
蕭無衣がこのまま無茶を続ければ
he probably won't even last
命は一年と
another year.
もたないだろう
Xiao Wuyi didn't mean to keep it from you.
蕭無衣はわざと黙っていたわけじゃない
Then how is he
それで今の彼は
now?
どうなの
It's well controlled.
経過は悪くない
In enclosed spaces or in the dark at night,
密室や夜など見えない状況だと
it worsens.
発作が増えるが
But he's learned to live with it.
もう慣れているはずだ
What worries me most now
今一番心配なのは
is that the Court of Judicial Review will use torture.
大理寺で拷問されることだ
I heard from Yuanji
元姫から聞いたが
that Commandant of Justice Lu is a harsh official.
あの陸廷尉は酷吏だとか
If Xiao Wuyi's condition worsens...
傷が悪化すれば
there's no telling what will happen.
どうなるか分からぬ
For now, the priority is finding a way to get him out
今すべきは一刻も早く
as soon as possible.
彼を救い出すことだ
Third Alley, Shanghe Ward has been emptied.
上河坊三巷はもぬけの殻
Grand Tutor Xie, you've fabricated charges.
太傅は罪をでっち上げ
You framed the Beifu Army commander who bled
血戦をくぐり抜けた北府の統帥に
for this nation as a traitor who colluded with the enemy.
国を裏切ったという濡れ衣を着せた
When you wake in the middle of the night,
夜半に夢から覚めても
doesn't your conscience ever trouble you?
良心は少しも痛まぬのか
Yaoyao, you're thoughtful.
夭夭よ ご苦労
A troubled conscience?
良心が痛むだと
I'm only doing to him what he once did to others.
わしは奴が昔やったことをやり返したにすぎん
You mean...
まさか
Prince Jing'an framed the An and Lu families?
靖安王が安陸の二氏を陥れた件
He knew there was an injustice in the An-Lu case,
奴は安陸の件に冤罪があると知りながら
yet he concealed it.
報告せずに隠蔽した
How is that any different from framing?
陥れたことと何が違う
And Xiao Wuyi.
それに蕭無衣だ
Since he is Crown Prince Wenxi,
奴が文熹太子である以上
he naturally must atone for
両親の
the sins committed by his birth parents.
犯した罪を償うのは当然だ
Yaoyao, concocting an unjust case
夭夭よ 冤罪のでっち上げとはな
might be unfair to others,
他の者には不公平かもしれぬ
but to the Xiao family
だが蕭氏や
and Crown Prince Wenxi,
文熹太子にとっては
it's Heaven's will.
天の思し召し
Heaven's justice always comes full circle—
天道は巡り
this is retribution.
因果応報よ
Father.
父上
What really happened
安陸の二氏に 当時
to the An and Lu families back then?
何があったのですか
Just as the Xiao family is experiencing today.
今の蕭氏が経験していることと 同じだ
My Lady, how did you know
お嬢様は なぜ
about the mechanism in Grand Tutor Xie's study?
太傅様の書斎の仕掛けを
I was mischievous as a child
幼い頃 いたずらをしていて
and stumbled upon the mechanism by accident.
偶然この仕掛けを見つけたのです
You know what's inside the box, My Lady?
箱の中身はご存じで
No.
存じません
But they must be extremely important to Grand Tutor Xie.
ですが きっと太傅様にとって この上なく大切な物のはず
Qizhou, Qingzhou...
岐州 青州
And Luzhou.
それに瀘州
Where did you go?
どこへ行っていたのだ
After His Highness was imprisoned,
世子の件の後
Qing Long and I were ordered to go to Luzhou to find someone.
私と青龍は命を受け 瀘州で人を捜していました
Who?
誰だ
Prince Qi's adoptive mother, Madam Wang of the Lu family.
岐王殿下の養母 盧王氏です
Originally, she'd always been under His Highness's control,
もとは世子の監視下にありましたが
but she was poisoned at some point.
いつの間にか毒殺されていました
We were still a step too late.
我々は一足遅かった
A step too late again.
また一足遅かったか
Actually, Her Highness Princess Yunzhao
実は郡主様も
also sent me to these three places
私にこの３か所へ赴き
to look for Madam Wang of the Lu family.
盧王氏を捜すよう命じられました
It was shortly after Prince Qi was appointed Regent.
岐王が監国に封じられて 間もなくのことです
That's also why
それゆえ
I didn't go to Lingfeng Fort with Her Highness.
私は郡主様と凌風堡には同行しなかったのです
What did Mother send you to do?
母上はそなたに何をさせた
To investigate Prince Qi's true identity.
岐王の出自の調査です
For Mao, for our family,
阿茂のため 謝氏のため
you must be this pawn.
そなたはこの駒とならねばならぬ
I finally understand
ようやく分かったわ
why Lejun killed my mother,
楽君が なぜ母上を殺そうとしたのか
why my father and mother
なぜ父上と母上が
divorced after I got married,
私の結婚後に離縁したのか
and why my mother never approved
母上が なぜずっと反対していたのか
of Mao and me being together.
私と阿茂が結ばれることに
I understand it all now.
すべて分かったわ
I, Xie Jiayu, Consort of the Heir of Prince Jing'an,
靖安王世子妃 謝嘉魚
pay respects to Regent Prince Qi.
監国 岐王殿下に拝謁いたします
Let her in.
通せ
The corruption and treason of
靖安王府の汚職と不正
Prince Jing'an's family have all been confirmed.
そして売国の件は事実と確認された
No matter how badly you want to save him,
そなたがどれほど彼を助けたくとも
Xiao Wuyi has no other choice
蕭無衣には北府軍の兵権を手放し
but to hand over the command of the Beifu Army
罪己状を差し出す以外に
and write a confession.
道はない
I came today
今日参ったのは
to give you something.
そなたに渡したいものがあるからだ
Xiao Wuyi has known your true identity all along.
蕭無衣は とうにそなたの正体を知っていた
If he wanted your position,
もしその地位を望むなら
it would've been his long ago.
今日まで待つはずがない
You trust him that much?
それほど蕭無衣を信じるか
The facts speak for themselves,
それが事実です
whether you believe them or not.
お信じになろうと なるまいと
And if I keep you here,
では 私がそなたをここに留め置けば
then all this evidence
その証拠とやらも
will mean nothing.
意味をなさなくなるな
Yaoyao, don't force me.
夭夭 私を追い詰めるな
I'm not the Li Mao I used to be.
私はもう昔の李茂ではない
If I can't get what I want,
欲しいものが手に入らぬなら
then we'll all go down together.
刺し違える覚悟だ
I'll give you one last chance.
最後の機会を与えよう
Take off those robes of the Heir's Consort,
その世子妃の衣装を脱ぎ捨て
leave Xiao Wuyi,
蕭無衣のもとを去り
and stay by my side forever.
永遠に私のそばに戻ってこい
Okay?
いいな
No.
いやだ
I also have the letters exchanged between Grand Tutor Xie
私の手にはまだ 太傅と岐王府の乳母が
and your wet nurse over the past dozen years.
この十数年間交わした文があります
He still doesn't know
太傅はまだ気づいていない
that I took the letters.
文を私が持ち去ったことを
I'll give you three days.
三日の猶予をやる
If, after three days,
三日後
Wuyi and the rest of the Xiao family have not returned
無衣さんと蕭家の人々が戻らず
and if the Court of Judicial Review has not cleared their name,
大理寺が靖安王府の潔白を証明せねば
then this record of your true identity,
この来歴の密書と
along with the letters between the Grand Tutor
太傅と岐王府の乳母が
and your wet nurse over the past dozen years,
この十数年 交わした書簡の内容は
will be spread throughout Jiankang.
剣慷中に知れ渡るだろう
Mao,
阿茂さん
whether I'm the Heir's Consort or not,
世子妃であろうとなかろうと
I'm still Xie Jiayu.
私は謝嘉魚よ
Whether I'm with Xiao Wuyi or not,
蕭無衣さんと一緒でもそうでなくても
I won't choose to enter the palace with you.
あなたとの入内は選びません
These past few years, I've traveled to many places
この数年 色々な所へ行き
and lived very happily.
とても楽しかったわ
Don't stay trapped in the past
過去に囚われないで
and let it become your obsession.
過去を心の鬼にしてはだめ
You were never this kind of person.
あなたは本来 そんな人ではなかった
Yaoyao came.
夭夭さんが来ていたわ
When did you
いつから
start suspecting my true identity?
私の出自を疑うようになったの
From the moment Prince Changsha mutinied to force the abdication
長沙王が謀反を起こし
and you were suddenly pushed to the position of Regent.
あなたが突然 監国の位に就けられた時からよ
I thought
てっきり
it was at least after Lejun got rid of Princess Yunzhao.
楽君が郡主を始末した後かと思っていたわ
I didn't expect it to be even earlier.
それより早かったとはね
That night,
あの夜
when I saw you in Jiankang Palace,
剣慷宮であなたを見た時
I was wondering:
思ったの
Grand Tutor Xie had been plotting for a long time,
謝太傅はかねてより画策していたのに
so why did he choose you specifically?
なぜ あなたを選んだのかと
As expected,
案の定
His Majesty immediately sent people to Qizhou
陛下はすぐさま岐州へ人を遣わし
to investigate your true identity.
あなたの素性を探らせた
Princess Yunzhao's Shadow Envoys also went
郡主の影使もそれに乗じて
and found out the truth they shouldn't have.
探るべきでない真実を突き止めたわ
But at that time, why didn't you...
でも なぜあの時
Why didn't I expose you
私を暴かなかったの
and make this crime of deceiving the emperor public?
君主を欺いた罪を公表しなかった
Because you and I have the same ambition.
私と同じ志を抱いていたからだ
What I cannot accomplish,
私が成し遂げられぬ事を
you can accomplish in my place.
あなたなら代わりに成せる
I don't need an incompetent good man
あの地位には
standing in that position.
無能な善人は要らない
Ambition, ruthless methods—
野心も 手段も
whoever holds that position needs both.
必要だ
I don't think there's anything wrong with your origins.
あなたの出自に何の問題もない
You don't care about the throne,
至尊の位など どうでもいい
but you need a helper.
だが 協力者が必要だった
So you chose me.
だから 私を選んだ
For your ambition,
あなたの志のために
I lost Yaoyao.
私は夭夭を失い
I lost the life I was meant to have!
人生も失った
I am not willing to be your puppet,
あなたの傀儡にはならない
and even less willing to accept that Yaoyao remains so devoted to you.
夭夭があなたに心酔しているのも許せない
She loves freedom more than anything,
あれほど自由を愛した人が
yet she's willing to be bound to your side
甘んじてあなたのそばに縛られ
and give everything for you!
すべてを捧げるなんて
Those noble clans thought that making peace with Northern Qin
名家は北秦と和睦すれば
could buy a corner of peace and prosperity.
一隅の繁栄が得られると思っている
But that's only a fleeting prosperity confined within Jiankang's walls.
だがそれは 剣慷城内の一時的な繁栄にすぎない
Beyond the city,
剣慷城の外では
countless people on the Northern Border
どれほどの北境の民が
still live amid war.
今も戦乱の中で暮らしているか
If we don't eliminate Northern Qin
北秦を滅ぼし
and reclaim our lost homeland,
故郷を取り戻さねば
there can never be true peace!
真の平和は訪れない
Yizhi,
易之
these were your own words
これは剣慷へ逃れる道中
while you were fleeing here.
あなたが私に言った言葉よ
It was you who forgot.
忘れたのは あなた自身
The person who chose you
あなたを選んだのは
was never me...
私ではない
but yourself.
あなた自身よ